<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
 ! Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
 ! contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
 ! this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 ! The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
 ! (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
 ! the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 !
 !      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 !
 ! Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 ! distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 ! WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 ! limitations under the License.
 !-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  
  <properties>
    <title>Woden Project Proposal</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
    <section name="Project Proposal">
       <p>March 2005.</p>

       <p>The <a href="index.html">Woden</a> project is proposed as a subproject of the <a 
          href="http://ws.apache.org">Apache Web Services Project</a> to develop a Java class library 
          for reading, manipulating, creating and writing WSDL documents, initially to support 
          <a href="http://www.w3.org/2002/ws/desc/">WSDL 2.0</a> but with the longer term aim of
          supporting past, present and future versions of WSDL.
       </p>  

       <p>There are two main deliverables: an API and an implementation. The Woden API will consist of a
          set of Java interfaces. The WSDL 2.0-specific portion of the Woden API will conform to the 
          <a href="http://www.w3.org/2002/ws/desc/">W3C WSDL 2.0 specification</a>. The implementation 
          will be a high performance implementation directly usable in other Apache projects such as 
          <a href="http://ws.apache.org/axis/">Axis2</a>. 
       </p>

       <p>Members of the <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/wsdl4j">WSDL4J</a> team, 
          <a href="http://ws.apache.org/axis/">Apache Axis</a>, 
          <a href="http://www.eclipse.org">Eclipse</a> and <a href="http://www.w3c.org">W3C</a> will
          collaborate on this project. The Axis2 community have already put some effort into a WSDL 2.0
          Architecture. The Eclipse Web Tools project has experience in developing WSDL validators and one
          of its members is also a member of the W3C WSDL 2.0 Working Group.
       </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Potential applications">
      <ul>
        <li>Axis2, build time emitters and runtime parsing</li>
        <li>Eclipse tools, WSDL editors</li>
        <li>vendor products</li>
        <li>user applications</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section name="About the name &quot;Woden&quot;">
      <ul>
        <li>Woden is a mnemonic for Web service Description (i.e. WoDen).</li>
        <li>Woden is a Norse god and naming the project after a god is in keeping with other WS-Apache project names like Apollo, Hermes and Muse.</li>
        <li>Woden invented a form of writing called Runes (i.e. a form of Description).</li>
        <li>The symbol CEN in Runes looks like "&lt;", a left angle bracket, which may suggest we can trace the origins of XML back to Woden!</li>
       </ul>
    </section>
    <section name="Rationale">
      <p>There are current requirements for a WSDL 2.0 processor (e.g. Axis2, Eclipse tools, the WSDL4J
         community). This demand is expected to increase when the W3C issues a Recommendation for WSDL 2.0.
      </p>

      <p>The W3C WSDL 2.0 specification is currently at the "Call for Implementations" stage, which expects
         two independent implementations before progressing to the implementation review stage and then on
         to a W3C Recommendation. A WSDL 2.0 Java implementation from Apache in response to this call could
         help verify the quality of the specification and improve its implementation experience.
      </p>

      <p>Previous WSDL processors have been version specific, such as WSDL4J which is tightly bound to 
         WSDL 1.1.  In the longer term the Woden project could take the experience gained developing
         previous WSDL processors and deliver a WSDL processing "framework" that could accommodate future
         WSDL specifications without the need to completely rewrite the processor.
      </p>

      <p>We anticipate that implementations of the Woden API will also be developed by other projects for
         specific applications (e.g. the Eclipse Web Tools project may develop an EMF based implementation
         to support WSDL 2.0 editors, as it has done with JWSDL for WSDL 1.1).  A common API will be a good
         candidate for future standardization on a WSDL processing API.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Scope">
      <p>In the short term, the scope of the Woden project is:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>A WSDL 2.0 API that will significantly cover the W3C WSDL 2.0 specification, including the
            WSDL 2.0 Component Model, Soap bindings and message exchange patterns and XSD schema 
            typing.</li>
        <li>A high performance implementation of the API with read-write capability, but optimized for
            run time applications rather than build time tooling.</li>
        <li>Fast, efficient XML parsing (e.g. StAX-based).</li>
        <li>A validator component that will provide optional WSDL validation, both schema validation
            and semantic validation.</li>
        <li>An Ant task for command line usage based on Ant XMLValidate.</li>
        <li>Support usability and flexibility across different usage scenarios through the handling of
            behaviour such as I/O, error reporting, progress monitoring, memory efficiency and thread
            safety.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Longer term, Woden's scope will include:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Full support for remaining parts of the W3C WSDL 2.0 specification, such as other protocol
            and type extensions.</li>
        <li>A Woden framework based on an extendable architecture that will allow for known or future
            versions of WSDL to be plugged in, rather than hard coded in the core of the WSDL processor
            (e.g. plugging in WSDL 1.1 support).</li>
        <li>A pluggable choice of XML parsing and object representation to support particular usage
            scenarios (e.g. a StAX-based, DOM-free XML model for a runtime application versus a 
            DOM-based model for build time tooling).</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section name="Initial Source">
      <p>IBM will donate the WSDL4J source code. Although WSDL4J is the reference implementation of 
         JSR110 (Java APIs for WSDL), Woden will not be an implementation of JSR110. WSDL4J is specific
         to WSDL 1.1 but some of the code and the intellectual property may be reused to develop a 
         WSDL 2.0 processor.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Resources to be created">
      <p>Mailing Lists: woden-dev, woden-user</p>

      <p>SVN Repository: ws-woden</p>

      <p>Issue Tracking: JIRA</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Apache Sponsor">
      <p>The Champion of the Woden incubator project is Davanum Srinivas (dims at apache.org).</p>

      <p>The Sponsor of Woden is the Apache Web Services PMC.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Initial Committers">
      <p>Chathura Herath (chathura at opensource.lk, WS-Apache Axis)<br/>
         Jeremy Hughes (hughesj at apache.org, WSDL4J)<br/>
         John Kaputin (jakaputin at gmail.com, WSDL4J)<br/>
         Lawrence Mandel (lmandel at ca.ibm.com, Eclipse Web Tools (WTP) / Eclipse Web Service Validation Tools (WSVT) )<br/>
         Arthur Ryman (arthur.ryman at gmail.com, Eclipse Web Tools (WTP) / W3C WSDL 2.0 Working Group)
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Incubator Mentors">
      <p>Paul Fremantle (pzf at hursley.ibm.com)<br/>
         Sanjiva Weerawarana (sanjiva at opensource.lk)
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Relevant links">
      <ul>
        <li>Eclipse Web Service Validation Tools (WSVT)
            - <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/wsvt">http://www.eclipse.org/wsvt</a></li>
        <li>Eclipse Web Tools (WTP) - <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/webtools">http://www.eclipse.org/webtools</a></li>
        <li>W3C WSDL 2.0 Working Group - <a href="http://www.w3.org/2002/ws/desc/">http://www.w3.org/2002/ws/desc/</a></li>
        <li>WSDL4J - <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/wsdl4j/">http://sourceforge.net/projects/wsdl4j/</a></li>
      </ul>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>


